Otilia Stretcu

Contact Details: otiliastr@gmail.com
Website: https://otiliastr.github.io

Languages: Romanian (native), English (fluent), Spanish (beginner), German (beginner), Swedish (beginner)

RESEARCH AREAS

My PhD research focuses on developing algorithms for machine learning, mainly focused on semi-supervised learning, curriculum learning, multitask learning, and graph-based problems. I am also passionate about applying machine learning methods in neuroscience, in order to study how the brain understands language and controls speech.

EDUCATION

2015-now Carnegie Mellon University - Ph.D. in Machine Learning

USA

- Co-advised by Prof. Barnabàs Pòczos and Prof. Tom Mitchell
- GPA: 4.0 (4.0 scale)

2015-17 Carnegie Mellon University - M.S. in Machine Learning

USA

- Co-advised by Prof. Barnabàs Pòczos and Prof. Tom Mitchell
- GPA: 4.0 (4.0 scale)
- Thesis: Understanding the Neural Basis of Speech Production Using Machine Learning
- Master's degree requirements completed while working towards obtaining my Ph.D.

2014-15 University of Cambridge - Master of Philosophy (M.Phil.) in Advanced Computer Science

UK

- Advised by Prof. Pietro Lió
- Thesis: Machine Learning Methods for Computational Microscopy
- Pass with Distinction

2010-14 Politehnica University of Timisoara - B.Eng. in Computer Science and Information Technology

Romania

- GPA: 9.98 (10.0 scale)
- 1st out of 140 students

2012-13 Linköping University - Erasmus Exchange Student

Sweden

I spent the third year of my undergraduate studies as an Erasmus exchange student at Linköping University, Sweden.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Spring 2019 Software Engineering Intern at Google AI Research

USA

- Part time internship in the Expander team in Google Al Research.
- Research on deep learning models for graph-based semi-supervised learning, published at NeurIPS 2019.

Summer 2018 Software Engineering Intern at Google Al Research

USA

- Expander team in Google Al Research, Mountain View, CA, USA.
- Research on deep learning models for graph-based semi-supervised learning.

Summer 2016 Software Engineering Intern at Google X

USA

- Self-Driving Car team in Google X (current Waymo), Mountain View, CA, USA.
- Undisclosed machine learning project for the Google self-driving car.

Summer 2014 Software Developer Intern at Microsoft

USA

- Cortana team at Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA.
- Undisclosed machine learning project for Cortana, Windows' digital personal assistant.

RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

* denotes equal contribution and joint lead authorship.

AAAI Contextual Parameter Generation for Knowledge Graph Link Prediction

2020

G. Stoica*, O. Stretcu*, E.A. Platanios*, T. Mitchell, B. Póczos

In Proceedings of the Thirty-fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 2020.

ICLR Coarse-to-Fine Curriculum Learning

O. Stretcu, E.A. Platanios, T. Mitchell, B. Póczos

In International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) Workshop on Bridging AI and Cognitive Science (BAICS), 2020.

NeurIPS 2019 **Graph Agreement Models for Semi-Supervised Learning** O. Stretcu, K. Viswanathan, D. Movshovitz-Attias, E.A. Platanios, S. Ravi, A. Tomkins In Proceedings of the Thirty-third Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, 2019. NeurIPS Contextual Parameter Generation for Knowledge Graph Link Prediction G. Stoica*, O. Stretcu*, E.A. Platanios*, T. Mitchell, B. Póczos In Neural Information Processing Systems Workshop on Graph Representation Learning, 2019. UAI Efficient Multitask Feature and Relationship Learning. H. Zhao, O. Stretcu, R. Negrinho, A. Smola, G. Gordon. In Proceedings of the 2019 Annual Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence 2019. **HBM** Investigating Task Effects on Brain Activity During Stimulus Presentation in MEG. 2019 O. Stretcu*, M. Toneva*, B. Póczos, and T. Mitchell. Accepted for poster presentation at the Human Brain Mapping Conference, 2019. NAACL Competence-based Curriculum Learning for Neural Machine Translation. E A. Platanios, O. Stretcu, G. Neubig, B. Póczos, and T. Mitchell. Oral presentation at the Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL), 2019. JNeurosci Subthalamic nucleus and sensorimotor cortex activity during speech production. A. Chrabaszcz, W. J. Neumann, O. Stretcu, W.J. Lipski, A. Bush, C. Dastolfo-Hromack, D. Wang, D. J. Crammond, S. Shaiman, M. Walsh Dickey, L.L. Holt, R. S. Turner, J.A. Fiez, and R. M. Richardson The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience, 2019. SDM **BRAINZOOM: High Resolution Reconstruction from Multi-modal Brain Signals** 2017 O. Stretcu*, X. Fu*, K. Huang*, H. Song*, E.E. Papalexakis, P. Talukdar, N.D. Sidiropoulos, C. Faloutsos, T. Mitchell, and B. Póczos. Oral presentation at SIAM International Conference on Data Mining (SDM), 2017 NeurIPS **Efficient Multitask Feature and Relationship Learning** H. Zhao, O. Stretcu, R. Negrinho, A. Smola, G. Gordon. NeurIPS Workshop on Learning with Limited Labeled Data: Weak Supervision and Beyond, 2017 CMU Understanding the neural basis of speech production using Machine Learning O. Stretcu. Master's Thesis in Machine Learning at Carnegie Mellon University, 2017 2015 **BMVC** Multiple Frames Matching for Object Discovery in Video. O. Stretcu, M. Leordeanu. In British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC), 2015.

OTHER RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

EMIM

2014-15 Independent Research Project in Computer Vision

O. Stretcu, Y. Shavit, and P. Lio

Romania

Research project in collaboration with Dr. Marius Leordeanu from the Institute of Mathematics of the Romanian Academy (IMAR).

Poster presentation at the 10th annual meeting of the European Society for Molecular Imaging (ESMI), 2015.

 Research on unsupervised object discovery in video based on multiple frames matching, published at BMVC 2015.

A multi-method driven evaluation of molecular imaging techniques.

Summer 2013 Research Internship in Machine Learning at EPFL

Switzerland

- Research internship at École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Laboratory for Probabilistic Machine Learning, advised by **Dr. Matthias Seeger**.
- I used topic models to explore the correlation between social media messages from Twitter and the location of the users, with applications to user profiling, topic tracking and content recommendation. I applied various machine learning models and parallelized the code in order to scale well.

Summer 2011 Research for Undergraduates Program

Romania

- Advised by Prof. Emilia Petrisor at Politehnica University of Timisoara, Romania.
- I implemented algorithms for spectral clustering of nodes in a graph, based on minimum graph cut, with applications to data mining and statistics, such as clustering information from documents on the Web and medical images segmentation.

HONORS AND AWARDS

FELLOWSHIPS

Center for Machine Learning and Health (CMLH) Fellowship in Digital Health (2018)

SCHOLARSHIPS

- Gates Cambridge Scholarship (2014)
- Google Anita Borg Memorial Scholarship (2013)
- GE (General Electric) Foundation Scholar Leaders Program (2012)

AWARDS

- Best poster award at the Eastern European Machine Learning Summer School in Bucharest, Romania (2019).
- Machine Learning Department Teaching Assistant Award (2018)
- Carnegie Mellon University Neurohackathon: 2nd place (2017)
- KTH University Programming Challenge, Sweden: Top 10 contestants (2013)
- ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest (ACM-ICPC): Honorable Mention in Southeastern European Regional (2013, 2012, 2011)
- Microsoft Imagine Cup: Top 20 in the World Finals (2012), 1st team in the Romanian National Finals (2012)
- Romanian National Olympiad in Informatics: Gold Medal (2008), Bronze Medal (2010), 1st Place (2004), 2nd Place (2005), Honorable Mention (2010, 2008, 2007, 2003)
- Kangaroo International Mathematical Competition: 2nd in Romanian National Finals (2009, 2010)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Spring 2018 Teaching Assistant for Graduate Machine Learning.

USA

- Graduate level introduction to machine learning class 10-701 Graduate Machine Learning at Carnegie Mellon University.
- Taught by Prof. Pradeep Ravikumar and Prof. Manuela Veloso
- I was awarded a Machine Learning Department Teaching Assistant Award.

Fall 2017 Teaching Assistant for Topics in Deep Learning.

USA

- Graduate level deep learning class 10-707 Topics in Deep Learning at Carnegie Mellon University.
- Taught by Prof. Ruslan Salakhutdinov.

2013-14 Teaching algorithms for competitive programming.

Romania

- Co-organized a competitive programming seminar at Politehnica University of Timisoara for university and high-school students interested to train for algorithmic competitions (e.g. ACM-ICPC, informatics olympiad).
- Taught algorithms and data structures used in competitive programming, designed and solved practice problems and internal competitions.

INVITED TALKS

- Invited talk at Health@Scale on Graph Agreement Models for Semi-Supervised Learning (2020)
- Represented CMU at the MIDAS Data Science Annual Symposium at the University of Michigan (2019).
- Talk at the CMU AI Seminar on Contextual Parameter Generation for Knowledge Graph Link Prediction (2019).

SERVICES

- Mentorship:
 - □ Mentor for the CMU AI mentoring program (2019–2020)
 - Mentor for first year PhD students at CMU (2019–2020)
- **Program Committees:** I was a reviewer for the following journals, conferences and workshops: ICML (2019), AISTATS (2019, 2020), ICLR (2018, 2020), ICLR-LLD (2019), PLOS ONE (2019), ICML-GRL (2020), NeurIPS (2020).
- Conference Workshops Organized: Adaptive & Multitask Learning at ICML 2019
- Other leadership and volunteering activities:
 - □ 2018-present: Founding member of the Al+ Club at Carnegie Mellon University (CMU).
 - 2016-present: Member of the Doctoral Review Committee of the Machine Learning Department at CMU.
 - □ 2018–2019: Treasurer of the Romanian Students Association at CMU.
 - $\ \square$ 2016–2018: President of the Romanian Students Association at CMU.
 - □ 2016—now: Member of the Education Review Committee of the Machine Learning Department at CMU, which aims to improve the PhD program.
 - □ 2011–12: Student representative in the faculty leadership board at Politehnica University of Timisoara.
 - □ 2010–11: Volunteer for AIESEC, international youth organization.
 - □ 2010–12: Volunteer for Liga AC, student organization at Politehnica University.

COMPUTER SKILLS

- **Programming languages**: C, C++, Python, Matlab, Java.
- **Data Structures and Algorithms**: Familiarity with concepts used in algorithmic competitions and machine learning research.
- Frameworks: TensorFlow, NumPy, SciPy, Pandas.
- Database Systems: MySQL.

TECHNICAL PROJECTS

- **LiveX Learning Platform**: Tutoring system for kindergarten and school children based on a software platform that runs in the cloud, Windows Phone 7 devices and a set of electronic learning cubes called "IQubes" (our hardware invention) as part of team IQube that competed in the world finals of the Microsoft Imagine Cup competition.
- Face and Hand Gesture Recognition for Human Computer Interaction: Framework for C++ developers to extend their graphical user interfaces with more natural means of communication. Works in real-time using a computer web camera.
- **Public Transport Route Recommendation**: Python application for the Timisoara city public transport system using real-time information from GPS devices installed on public transport vehicles. Overlays optimal routes suggestions on Google Maps (before they supported such a feature).
- Handwritten digits recognition: C library implementing various linear algebra methods for handwritten digits recognition.

OTHER INTERESTS

- Sports: squash, volleyball, tennis, climbing, hiking.
- Hobbies: traveling, painting, movies, arts and crafts.